there's a confusion around emotions and
feelings feelings emotions
and people summers wonder what is the
pali word for emotions and it's and some
translators translate the word chitter
the party with chitta
as emotion all right good it's the heart
rise out of my emotions right so the
emotional being the mind but there's a
well know the the the emotions I mean
based on its own
etymology just means like an intense
feeling so if you're emotional
emotionally positive emotionally
negative so is a kind of mind state but
on the basis of I feel just amplified so
to speak but also I think if you if you
if you were to ask uh psychotherapy or a
song I think things got extremely
convoluted a word like emotions our
subconscious unconscious physiological
and it is just like something's
unconscious how can you talk about
consciously I don't even know it no it's
just the amplified feelings so if you if
you cultivate see your responses to
feelings you're basically calculating an
attitude of being emotional
that's why you need to keep giving in to
your feelings in order to become more
eventually then you don't have to
emotions will be automatic those mental
states will be instantaneous when
touched by unpleasant feeling on the
touch the pleasant feeling because you
cultivated it because it doesn't matter
the complexity of an emotion it's always
within the feeling it's always or how is
this emotional complex subconsciously
unconscious state felt consciously felt
pleasant that's the doorway that's the
framework for any emotion any direction
you can take any action you can do on
account of it so you don't need to worry
about this emotion or that emotion you
just need to see whether your actions
are rooted in avoiding displeasure
prolonging pain or prolonging pleasure
and sort of trying to distract yourself
from a neutral feeling if you start
practicing on that level all of your
emotionality will subside
same for example like the satipatthana
he knows a lustful mind as a lustful
mind so you say he knows an emotional
mindless ain't mine yeah you could say
yeah but then you basically even bet any
state of mind it's underlined by a
certain way it's felt so you say he
knows the lated mind is a latent mind
depressed man and depressed mind how the
latent mind felt is it elated in a
positive sense or a negative sense so
yeah contemplation of the mind is
inseparable from contemplation to
feeling or thoughts or the body for that
matter that's where it's at the katana
it's it's the four foundations like one
one and a half but the point is you
whatever for you
designation would term emotion means you
just want to see past it as in see
beyond it and how how it simultaneously
felt it's emotional you already know
whether it's Pleasant implies whether
you want it to stay longer whether
you're riding the wave or for for
pleasure and excitement or you're
basically absolutely trying to get rid
of it at all costs you're emotionally
disturbed distraught so just didn't say
I feel angry I have the emotion yeah you
can say emotion of anger sure so I'm
emotionally angry yeah so what I do well
you stop what I have to get rid of the
pain of that anger or that emotion but
what about if I just am aware that I'm
angry well I suppose that's the first step but
well I suppose that's the first step but
that won't do anything let's just make
you aware of the anger yeah you need to
become aware of self aware of whatever
you're feeling whatever you state in you
need to become aware of the problem in
order to deal the problem but being
aware of the problem this - or the
problem I'm aware of that I'm aware of
the problem yeah but I need to be more
aware of the problem so that I can
actually see the way out more often than
not that's the case yeah you need to be
more aware of the whole you need to make
them you need to make it a bit of like a
recognize and this is a serious problem
because otherwise you will not master
enough determination
to keep drilling in the direction and
undo it it's easier to forget about
especially when that emotion has
subsided that's why the Buddha the
divine messenger something need to
reflect on before you get sick before
you get old and before you're dead you
need to recognize that you are liable to
be sick live I'm liable to lust I'm
liable to anger that's I need to
recognize before these things occur so
basically so I cannot prove them so they
don't occur anymore but yeah in order to
recognize that you're liable to these
things the first step is to be aware of
them when they are present but thinking
that just by being aware when they are
present you somehow dealing with it will
then not make you think about it when
those are things are not present you
think you're fine
because now I'm not angry see but is it
because you are polluted be the basis
for anger but simply because the
circumstances are currently soothing you
and going the way you want them to be
make now you emotionally you're getting
emotional about that yeah yeah yeah so
you would still be disturbed or on some
account if things were to change and
they will have to change so what about
that idea brought up earlier evers
emotions shaped the mind emotion is the
shape of the mind meaning that it
actually constricts the mind the clouds
the mind yeah because it's given our
shape which is twisted and you know it's
twisted in its particular way it's kind
of wrong it's it lacks perspective Yoga
has stunted than expected so by removing
the root cause for the emotion you will
then remove the root cause for the
reduction of your perspective caused by
the emotion when you're emotional but if
you say he's no longer emotional you
have a larger perspective no more
narrowed a response or
automatic response to however you feel
there is no shape then it is that that
mind is to no longer constricted well
yeah well the mind is not only
constricted but it more like you are not
constricted in regards to the shape of
the mind the mind still will have some
shape for as long as the mind is there
but the certain shapes will not restrict
the mind anymore so that's how you
liberate your understanding but your
understanding liberates you so inside
the putana you know depressed
constricted restricted mind as depressed
constricted restricted mind so you are
not depressed restricted and restricted
by it say farmer like no in the presence
of hindrances for example that's how you
understand the way out of them not like
they never arise on the level of the
body it's just whatever arises on that
level of the body that whatever's being
experienced it cannot restrict you
anymore because you know the escape well
yeah the only reason you were it was
restricting you is because you
restricted yourself by giving in to
getting trying to get rid of craving
against the unpleasant feeling so the
hindrances track view but not fight by
like by their own effort they like set
up traps and you keep stepping into it
by giving into craving against the
discomfort craving for the comfort
that's how you trap yourself within the
domain of hindrances that's how you trap
yourself within these random shapes of
the mind that arise with these little
random weather literally like weather
mine emotions if you want to call it
even moods are the weather sometimes
it's sunny sometimes it's hot sometimes
cold sometimes windy sometimes it rains
neither of those weather circumstances
conditions need to be affecting how you
like your responses your feelings you
your thoughts and what you try to deal
with it could make no difference if you
go beyond it I don't mind if it's rain I
don't mind if it's sunny like I remain
untouched by that you're not excited or
depressed exactly I don't wish for rain
and cry when it's too hot
nor do I
cry when it's rainy and get all
depressed when things are wet so when
you experience a disagreeable thing hmm
disagreeable you don't get so late in
mind is known as a late in mind the
first - the first mind neither relate to
no the first neither later at the fest
so in a sense be having emotions can be
assigned for that's a symptom yeah ah
this is it so you don't need to deal
with that but you need to start looking
what else is there beyond that that is
the net that is the more of a problem
then these emotions are the symptom of a
problem so what is there like emotions
it led to the way that comes you can't
stop it's not because you've done
something wrong and it started to rain
but do you want to see but is there
anything that I am doing that's
responsible for me being affected by
these emotions but these weather by
these moods they come and go and then
you realize that there is like you'll be
affected by rain only when you crave for
doing things on the card of sunny good
weather if you don't really mind it will not be
if you don't really mind it will not be
affected by window weather changes
because it doesn't affect you you were
not committed to emotionally to things
you want to do for the sake of comfort
pleasure which requires sunshine which
require good weather which cannot be
done in the rain but say alternatively
if you're a bit tired of work tired of
people you want rain is that everything
stops everything goes quiet nobody comes
nobody goes anywhere oh then you would
want to rain and then when the Sun comes
people wake up and start going left and
right and coming to your place you will
no wonder so the on some occasion the
same way that makes you happy it makes
you sad why is that it's not because of
the weather if things were truly routine
the weather you will always be happy
when it's a certain weather when it's a
certain shape of the mind where it's a
certain stage of the mind but you work
so you are happy based on basically
where you're craving has projected your
expectation it's pretty much craving
it'll tell in how you feel and how you
want to avoid
so getting emotional can show you in
with direction you need to be
questioning things show you where the
problem is so you're liable to emotions
you have a problem you know emotions
will not have a reason without a
necessary basis of present enduring
craving for that against or for that
certain feeling that's there so let's
say if you got emotional that can only
be done on the level of it can be done
on the basis of you craving against the
displeasure or pleasure
the craving for pleasure
so once that craving is removed or
diminished diminished gradually
gradually maybe less and less emotional
you'll be pulling down yes so and more
you can't be emotional by the way
without having passion so I reckon they
regard emotions as the symptoms or you
can regard a passion as a symptom so you
can say if there is craving in regard to
how you're feeling
whatever you're feeling at the time
present enduring there is passion there
is emotion to what extent well that's
determined by the extent of your
ignorance of your own craving is
determined by the extent you took your
own feelings for granted as something to
be wished for delighted in or something
to be resisted and got rid of yes so
forth but being emotional motionless
seems to be in that second probably fear
most like you don't just wanna be
depressed yeah because from their
forehead you say yes it described the
idea any idea of emotionless Ness is is
judged by its discerned is discriminated
against the background of what they know
which is emotions so from the point of
view of emotions it's like it feels like
look from the point of your passion
being passion free passion less it's
like well that's like death from the
point of your passion because it is from
the point of your fashion that is who
you are it is less of the passion which
you are so it's death of you the way you
know yourself but you have a choice you
can either practice towards the death of
passion or you can stay out of fear not
go there and then be liable to
everything else that passion is
basically direct cause off the entire
some sort of suffering liability torment
despair lamentation that the
so because you're afraid to die because
you're afraid to let your passions and
emotions die your bond to actually die
you bind yourself to death because
you're afraid
because that's how you reach deathless
as the little Excel that's how death
does not apply to you anymore
extinguishing passions and emotions
peril
so you got you should not act out your
emotions because you're not act
yeah the first step you should not like
that even more join yourself you should
become aware of them
well like while they're enduring
especially that's how you don't act out
of them well you should also see them as
a symptom of an underlying problem but
you know have you seen that all look
just being aware of it and enduring it
somehow I'm dealing with it because they
were not a problem so if you think that
the symptoms are the problem you're not
going to look for what the real problem
is the cause of these symptoms so pretty
much unless you're free from suffering a
lesson to stood the four noble truths
and became sort of honor everything you
think is a problem is really a symptom
of problem again when you suffer
suffering a symptom of liability to
suffering
because that's what the problem is
that's where you suffer in the first
place because you were liable to suffer
but that's to cut
that's what defensive yeah we exhaust
their symptoms of where suffering is the
symptom of dukkha and du prais the
problem so freedom from dukkha then
means freedom from symptoms of doping
which is fear from suffering it's it's
an unfortunate translation I mean it
kind of yeah you could say that because
symptoms of suffering symptoms of Duke
are suffering - Chris all suffering sure
but it's not in the same level dukkha
there needs to be understood is a dead
level in the level of that liability -
that's what was it the wise men would
say I am subject to suffering I'm
subject to misfortune like nothing has
happened to me but it could I am I am
subjected to the possibility of these
things happen afraid I'm afraid to
suffering exactly but if people just
confuse dukkha to be the suffering
that's just felt sometimes felt
sometimes isn't they're not looking for
what the real problem is so literally
then the problem is only when you're
being attacked by a lion you don't
recognize that the problem is that the
lion can pounce on you at any given time
that's sort of the problem and that's
the only reason why the lion eventually
did attack you could you remained within
the Lions boundary where the lion hunts
but even before the lion attacks you if
you recognize that this is the hunting
ground of the lion means I am liable to
it I better do something about it before
lion attacks me that's what the play is
that recognition of that so literally
the comings on ease like suka means ease
Duke raise the opposite said this is an
ease and that's exactly so there's
nothing wrong me I'm not being mauled by
lion yet but I recognize that this is
literally the stomping ground of wild
cats they hunt people
I am prey to that the recognition that
will make you very uneasy but it's much
easier to just ignore that because
anxiety fear dread
or how they do this because you can't
just hide you're still getting the same
hunting ground you have to step outside
eventually and you still step outside
into the area of they will kill you so
it's easier to ignore them that that
anxious recognition of that uneasiness
that you are prey to suffering of any
kind and then just focus on the present
moment what I was presently resonant
with wishful thinking that everything
will work out so literally then you wait
for things to arise in order to practice
oh I'm feeling this right now well the
feeling is come now the feeling has
passed away as if passing away the
feeling meant you dealt with it somehow
no means okay so you evaded another tank
of a lion so you got there does that
mean now you're not liable to another
attack yes so if you were attacked by a
line you got away he recognized it that
was sort of way now and you're keeping
evading evading evading and say well
don't suffer as much exactly I must be I
became very skilled in hiding away from
a lion yeah yeah but the only reason if
to do that is because you're still
within the line of Examiners so the
Buddhist practice takes you out of the
dukkha takes you out of the Lions
grounds and then you don't need to
that's true burden can see you might be
skillful at evading the lion but you're
constantly burdened by the duty of you
need to hide one slip one error you're
done and bottom line is deep down you
know eventually we'll have to get you we
will get you as if that's the divine
messengers with the sickness agent you
can't hide from that you can hide from
everything else in between semi
successfully so if your practice never
makes you realize oh it's about
liability to suffer being prey to
suffering as the Buddha would say you
know practising you're just managing and
that's not the practice practice of
brutes things practice doesn't manage
so yeah so so the fact that you go
throughout your day without experiencing
much lust without experiencing much
anger we don't experience see much
suffering of any kind it means nothing
is it because you have step outside of
the domain where you were to pray to
these process of futures as in is it
because it's impossible for you to
suffer it because you're not liable to
future loss diversion delusion well it's
simply because circumstances suits you
which one is it and if you look at it
honestly you already know the answer but
it's easy to think that well see since I
discovered Buddhism I don't suffer as
much or why is that because I understood
the nature of that this is that uneasy
that prey to suffering of any kind or
because you know I'm bit more carefully
what I do or say practice restraint and
live in this protected spiritual
community of the environment which one
is it so am i internally free from
suffering or just external have external
buffer zones come and again if you're
honest the answer will be quite simple
and obvious it's already there because
if you know internal internally that
you're free you're outside you know how
to escape the domain of line not even a
specific lion why would you worry about
specific lion which might jump on you
when you don't live where the Lions hunt
so keeping that image of lions being
inside the lion enclosure so to speak
yeah so you can you can game reserve
yeah and you can describe all the ways
that a lion can Maul you or the lion can
catch you you know I recognize all the
different ways that you can suffer yeah
and you simply enrich tuna conjugate but
fundamentally nothing has changed you
still doesn't matter if you know which
how many ways Lions can sort of drag you
around and kill you is to the point is
just de lisle and you're going to in
subjected to the possibility of one of
those ways of lying to you so it's not
about study studying the ways you can
suffer it's about recognizing that you
can suffer
. on account of anyway
so what is it that's why the naam is the
nature of things it's not the specific
manifestation or that that's within the
nature so you want to understand how to
be free from these things you need to
understand the nature of it so what is
the nature of you being afraid to Lions
hunting well the nature is that you are
within the lines domain can Lions get
you if you're not within their enclosure
if you're outside of their game reserve
if you abandon it if you feed yourself
from it you broke broke away impossible
for Lions to hunt you down so why are
you in that enclosure
well because you don't recognize that
you are prey to suffering you don't
recognize that you pray and you thought
recognizing your prey because that's
fixed people out when you don't remove
that that's what people would freak out
when the Buddha would teach them and the
minds were not ready but Rick so
recognizing that you are up tre
basically ignoring what the real problem
is that's why you remain under that
problem so the problem is that you are
liable to suffering not what
specifically your own account of what
specific thing you suffer but but
understand that you've somehow know no
longer be a prey
how can you no longer be afraid to the
lion how can you no longer be what by
understanding like what the extent of
the Lions domain understanding the
extent of the dukkha you will understand
what the freedom from their body escape
from the Duke is so then the the truth
that you will discover the Four Noble
Truths basically but let's keep with the
simile would be oh the only reason the
lions can hunt you down and will
eventually is because you yourself keep
yourself in that game deserve
then you keep yourself there because you
what because you value pleasures that
you get there you know it has nice
fruits good company beautiful views and
adventure lovely streams yeah whatever
basically gets you going
it has it but at the same time it has
lines that are stoking you and hunting
you down so so no longer if you were to
not forget that there Lyons might be
watching you at any given time no amount
of this joyful pleasures that that game
deserve can offer will be enough for you
to stay there but what happens is most
of the time you don't see the Lions so
you afford to forget that you are still
a prey to the Lions even if you don't
see them so by affording to forget that
you then afford to be attracted and
appreciate all these beauties of senses
that you can get from that Game Reserve
and it's literally forgetting that
you're liable to death modern and modern
new sati it's exactly that you don't see
that so you don't think about it by now
thinking about it you maintain the whole
world of sensuality anger this for
everything else but if you were not to
forget that you're liable to die at any
given second and in breath out breath as
the Buddha would say any attraction you
have on account of being alive any
passion will have to disappear
eventually it will wither away because
you're not maintaining it in